<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<course-standard id="AL-G5-SCIENCE">
  <description>Alabama Science, Grade 5, 2005 standard expanded by Melissa 
Bryan to cover objectives which are not part of the standard but which
are part of the year-end test, and to provide an example breakdown of
some of the broader objectives in the standard into smaller objectives
</description>

  <source>http://alex.state.al.us/standardAll.php?grade=5&amp;subject=S1&amp;summary=2</source>

  <category>K12-S</category>

  <objectives>
    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-01">
      <description>Identify evidence of physical changes (changes in which no
new substance is formed).  Identify evidence of chemical changes through color,
gas formation, solid formation, and temperature change.  Examples of physical 
and chemical changes: A nail being hammered into a piece of wood; combining 
vinegar and baking soda to produce a gas.
      </description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-02A">
      <description>Describe matter.  Identify the six states of matter &#x2014; 
solids, liquids, gases, colloids, plasma, Bose-Einstein condensates.  Identify
atoms and molecules.  Identify the atom as the basic building block of matter.
Understand that particle motion is related to temperature.
</description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-02B">
      <description>Describe mass.
      </description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-02C">
      <description>Describe volume.
      </description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-02D">
      <description>Describe density.  Relate density to the sinking or floating
of an object in a liquid.
      </description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-03">
      <description>Use everyday indicators such as red cabbage juice, black tea
or coffee, litmus paper, and grape juice to identify common acids and bases.
Examples: using grape juice to determine that vinegar is an acid, using juice
from boiled red cabbage to determine that baking soda is a base.
      </description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-04A">
      <description>
Describe energy and identify types of potential and kinetic energy.
Examples of potential energy: water behind a dam, battery.
Example of kinetic energy: water moving across turbine blades.
      </description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-04B">
      <description>Describe forms of energy, including chemical, heat, light, 
and mechanical.
      </description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-04C">
      <description>
Identify the transfer of energy by conduction, convection, and radiation.
Example of conduction: hot plate heating a pan.  Example of convection:
space heater heating air.  Example of radiation: sun heating Earth's surface.
      </description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-04D">
      <description>
Describe alternatives to the use of fossil fuels.  Examples: solar energy,
geothermal energy, windmill, hydroelectric power, biomass, and wave energy.
      </description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-04E">
      <description>Describe conservation of energy, especially of non-renewable
energy sources, typically fossil fuels.
      </description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-05A">
      <description>Describe light and the 3 ways it travels &#x2014; reflection,
absorption, and refraction (the bending of light).
      </description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-05B">
      <description>
Describe how a prism forms a visible spectrum (ROYGBIV).  Explain why different
objects have different colors.  Describe how mirrors reflect light, including
discussing differences in the reflection of light by convex and concave mirrors.
      </description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-05C">
      <description>Contrast ways in which light rays are bent by concave and
convex lenses.  Identify the contribution of van Leeuwenhoek to the development
of the microscope.
      </description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-05D">
      <description>Identify major parts of the eye (cornea, pupil, iris, retina, 
and optic nerve) and describe the relationship between the structure of the eye
and sight.
      </description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-05E">
      <description>Identify types of corrective lenses used to correct
different sight problems (convex for farsightedness, and concave for
nearsightedness).  Describe how and why the light rays are bent by these types
of corrective lenses.
      </description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-06">
      <description>Compare effects of gravitational force on Earth, on the moon
(the cause of tides on Earth), and within space.
Identify contributions of Newton to the study of gravity.
Describe how a spring scale is used to measure weight.
Explain friction and how air resistance affects falling objects.
      </description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-07A">
      <description>Identify major parts of plant and animal cells, including the
nucleus, cytoplasm, cell membrane, mitochondria, cell wall, chloroplast, and
vacuole.  Compare plant and animal cells.
      </description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-07B">
      <description>Compare unicellular and multicellular organisms.
Cells to tissues to organs to organ systems.
      </description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-08A">
      <description>Identify the digestive system as a major body system,
including main parts and functions.
      </description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-08B">
      <description>Identify the respiratory system as a major body system,
including main parts and functions.
      </description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-08C">
      <description>Identify the curculatory system as a major body system,
including main parts and functions.
      </description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-08D">
      <description>Identify the skeletal system as a major body system,
including main parts and functions.
      </description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-08E">
      <description>Identify the muscular system as a major body system,
including main parts and functions.
      </description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-08F">
      <description>Identify the excretory system as a major body system,
including main parts and functions.
      </description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-08G">
      <description>Identify the reproductive system as a major body system
which produces offspring.
      </description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-09A">
      <description>Describe the relationship of populations within a habitat to
various communities and ecosystems.  Describe the relationship between food
chains and food webs.
</description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-09B">
      <description>Describe these symbiotic relationships: commensalism
(one benefits, the other is not harmed), mutualism (both benefit), and
parasitism (one benefits and the other is harmed).
      </description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-10A">
      <description>Identify the geosphere.  Describe the layers of the earth and
the rock cycle.  Describe technology used to investigate the geosphere, 
including seismographs.
      </description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-10B">
      <description>Identify the atmosphere.  Describe the layers of the
atmosphere.  Describe technology used to investigate the atmosphere, such as
radar, satellites, and weather balloons.
      </description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-10C">
      <description>Identify the hydrosphere, including the water cycle.
Describe technology used to investigate the hydrosphere, including sonar.
      </description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-11A">
      <description>Identify the eight planets in order from the sun, and compare
distances from the sun to planets in our solar system.  Relate the size of Earth
to the size of other planets in our solar system.
      </description>
    </objective>

    <objective id="AL-G5-SCIENCE-11B">
      <description>Identify technology used to study planets, such as the Hubble
telescope, space probes, Mars Exploration Rover, and lunar rovers.
      </description>
    </objective>
  </objectives>
</course-standard>
